[Music]
Stanford
University all right so what is particle
physics about particle physics is about
particles it's about the question and
this is a very ancient question at least
I suspect about 2500 years old is nature
discreet discreet meaning to say not
that it's polite but that uh that it um
that matter and substances and energy
they didn't think about energy but they
thought about matter that matter comes
in discrete units in
indivisible uh units which of course the
Greeks called Adam I'm told that the
word Adam means indivisible despite the
fact that of course we break up atoms
all the time nevertheless that was the
origin of the word indivisible
that um all things in the universe are
made up out of something discrete let's
call them particles particles is a good
name for something discrete something
indivisible that
idea is as I said extremely
ancient the opposite idea is also
ancient again I don't know precisely
when it was first formulated I happen to
remember a little more about the history
the atomic idea that was it doesn't
matter who it is incidentally do not
trust my
history not because I don't know the
history but I sometimes tell the history
in which um in which I organize things
logically rather than rather than
temporarily so don't trust uh the time
sequence that I tell you it often
represents what I wish the time sequence
was rather than what it actually was but
it's it's good for being to present the
lot logic of what happened to presented
in a logically compelling way rather
than a uh a strict historical way in any
case uh there were these characters who
were the
atomists and the the opposite of them
the people who thought that matter
material and so forth was continuously
distributed continuously distributed
means simply not made up out of discret
elements but I don't know what the right
word is uniform continuous is the right
way right word a shmear as my
grandmother would have said a shmear
smeared out over a space in some uniform
continuous kind of way and we might call
that the field theory of matter Fields
what are Fields fields are functions in
space for example they could be the
density of
material uh in in a given region of
space they could be the electric and
magnetic fields those are good examples
electric and magnetic fields that
determine how charged particles move but
the fields themselves the electric and
magnetic fields are things that we
conceive of as being uniformly
distributed in space not uh not in the
form of
particles and so perhaps matter liquids
solids and so forth are also in some
sense continuous just like the
electromagnetic field that was the
opposite
idea
uh the particle idea the discrete idea
had words like molecules atoms and so
forth
collisions um and particles the
Continuum idea Continuum is the right
word the Continuum idea had words like
Fields attached to it uh continuous
fields of properties of of various
kinds which turned out to be right in
some sense neither and both in some
sense neither and both turned out to be
right the subtleties of quantum
mechanics got in the way of either of
them being completely right but it also
got in the way of either of them being
completely wrong quantum mechanics is a
subtle and difficult
subject uh as are many of the
preliminaries to particle physics I
think I have taught all of them by now
several times and they do exist on the
internet the internet uh lectures that
I've given they're out there and um I
advise you as I said I will try to keep
itself contained but I am going to
assume to some extent the knowledge that
I have taught previously in these
classes it can be picked up off the
internet very easily uh I I don't know
how to do it I couldn't do it for the
life of me I can never access my own
lectures but everybody else can do it
and uh well the real reason is I don't
like looking at myself so I never I
never do open my own lectures but
they're out there and they're fairly
complete there are at least two courses
out there on quantum
mechanics I think one on classical uh
mechanics at least one on special theory
of relativity and uh and electromagnet
ISM so since I put that effort in I'm
now going to try to uh draw on it not
today but uh in the
future and use many of the things that I
have lectured
about okay uh as I said the particle
physics question is whether nature is
discret or not let's just do a little
bit of History which I will probably get
wrong but uh that's at least um
chronologically to my knowledge the
first real evidence again it's to my
knowledge the first real evidence that
matter was discreete came of course from
chemistry it didn't come from physics it
came from
chemistry uh the division between
chemistry and physics is a highly
artificial one chemistry is simply just
the basically the physics of atoms and
molecules but uh it came from the
chemist uh well John John Dalton John I
think John Dalton who realized that the
masses of chemicals the mass of a given
number of molecules a given number of
molecules now how he knew that he was
had to deal with a given number of
molecules when he might be talking on
the one hand of hydrogen the other hand
of a carbon dioxide or something how he
knew it was a given number of molecules
is itself a story of a gad's name comes
into it and so forth the word mole not
the creature that lives under the ground
but the the uh uh the mole is avagadro's
number of molecules how they knew how
many molecules they didn't know how many
molecules but how they knew how to
compare different substances and say
both of them had the same number of
molecules that itself is an interesting
story but it's not the story I want to
tell the story I want to tell had to do
with the mass of a mole of material a
mass of a given number avagadro's number
of
molecules that came in discrete
multiples of the mass of a mole of
hydrogen now not exactly but close
enough to a pretty good
Precision uh the mass of a mole of
Goble is a integer multiple not three
not three halves not Pi not the not some
other silly number but some integer
times the the mass of the same number of
molecules of hydrogen that sort of
suggested to Dalton that there were
building
blocks that uh carbon what is it carbon
8 carbon 12 carbon 12 had 12 units of
whatever uh hydrogen one had hydrogen
was one unit of stuff whatever that
stuff was carbon 12 and whatever
whatever the other numbers were so it
seemed like things were being built up
out of basic units which basically had
the same mass as a hydrogen atom almost
as though everything was made up out of
units of
hydrogen uh Dalton I think proposed
something like that that there were
basic units and those basic units had
the mass roughly of a hydrogen
atom so that was the first bit of
evidence and of course this was
essentially
right today we understand let me just
tell you why that's true from today's
perspective not to make a mystery out of
it uh everything is made out of atoms
and atoms are made out of protons
neutrons and
electrons electrons are very very light
compared to protons and neutrons and in
counting up the mass of an atom the
electrons are not very significant an
electron has about a mass of 1
12,000th of no one yeah 1 1200 1
1200th of the mass of a proton or a
neutron so electrons don't come into the
equation they do come into the equation
but only a very very small term forget
about them protons and neutrons
constitute most of the mass almost all
of the mass of ordinary
material on the other hand protons and
neutrons surprisingly there's no well
there is a good reason for it but uh but
at the time there was certainly no known
reason in fact protons and neutrons
weren't known but protons and neutrons
have about the same mass as each
other as I said about 2,000 times the
mass of an
electron and so the mass of a molecule
is basically the mass of protons plus
neutrons they have about the same mass
and therefore the mass of a molecule is
an integer multiple of the mass of a
proton and neutron on the other hand
hydrogen is the nucleus of hydrogen is
just one proton and so it did turn out
that Dalton was right all materials have
a mass which is approximately there's an
approximation in there protons and
neutrons don't have quite the same mass
slightly different less than a percent
incidentally a tenth of a percent or
even less uh whereas electrons are so
light that they don't come into it very
much and so Dalton was right and there
was the first to my knowledge the first
real evidence that matter came in
discrete
units okay now molecules weren't atoms
of course took a little while longer to
find out that molecules were made up out
of atoms and the atoms weren't just
protons and neutrons or hydrogen that
atoms themselves the things we now call
atoms that there were about a hundred of
them 100 different kinds
this was of course the great Triumph of
chemistry of the 19th century and early
20th century to identify all of the
elements that go into the periodic table
up there incidentally the periodic table
is not very
periodic uh you know if you really look
at it it's it's a bit of a fake the
periodic table it's not very
periodic uh but nevertheless identifying
all those separate atoms up there the
elements the elements in some things
which are composed of all the same kind
you know that story composed of atoms
and identifying the atoms and at the end
of the identification of atoms roughly
about a hundred of them less than 100 uh
occurring in nature uh 92 of them to be
precise well more than that if you
include
Isotopes but of water a 100 different
kinds of
atoms and everything made up out of
atoms so atoms at the end of the 19th
century the things we call atoms or
elements were the building blocks the
elementary particles of nature now of
course it took another 5 years after the
turn of the century for Einstein to do
something that nailed really really
nailed the molecular theory of
matter it wasn't until
1905 that Einstein explained in detail
how you could prove that matter was
really made out of
particles but uh long before that
chemists physicists understood for the
most part that um that everything was
made out of these 92 elements so they
were the elementary particles Now sort
of all hell broke loose in the beginning
of the 20th century very very end of the
19th century when some discoveries were
made the electron was discovered
about three years I think before the
turn of the century I don't I don't know
exactly when it was the electron was
discovered and a number of other things
were discovered but in particular
radioactivity was discovered
radioactivity was the first
real uh
signal of the thing which was later to
become Nuclear
Physics uh and nuclear physics and
particle physics and had all the things
that needed to be explained sort of
there in a in a sort of tiny tiny little
version so let me just remind you about
radioactivity just for fun uh who was it
who discovered radioactivity I don't
know you
remember I don't think it was Marie cury
who discovered radioactivity I don't
think so H was it
Beckel I think it was Beckel yeah was
Mar cury she what she did was you know
lots and lots of experiments to pin it
down with great but it was it was
Beckel and he had a chunk of lead don't
ask me why he did this I do not know he
had a chunk of lead and a little hole in
the chunk of lead like that and some
material down here radioactive I guess
the first thing that happened was he had
some radioactive material presumably
radium or something like it and his
labor atory and he had a photographic
plate and accidentally the photographic
plate happened to be near the
uh uh the material not here over here
material photographic plate and the
photographic plate got
ruined but ruined by the presence of the
radioactive material the radioactive
material um just ruined you know was
like light shining on it and ruined the
photographic plate anybody else or not
anybody else probably me would have just
thrown away the the the plate and said
ah this is ruined let's find another
plate and start the experiment over
again but Beckel realized he had
discovered something he had discovered
that radioactive materials do something
to the photographic plate as if they had
been illuminated by some
radiation so he decided to study that
radiation a little bit better and he put
the source of it deep in a block of lead
how he knew to use lead I do not know
but lead was a good substance because
it's very dense
and he put it into a hole drilled into
the lead and then put his photographic
plate out here and uh wanted to see
whether it would illuminate a single
spot over here you know everything was
columnated by this hole he wanted to see
whether it would uh uh create a sharp
little spot as if something were coming
up out of this hole and indeed it did so
he got the idea that a beam of some sort
was being
ejected or something was being ejected
by this radioactive material and being
columnated along a
beam that was the first particle beam
that was the first beam of particles all
right what was it he had no idea what it
was but then I guess a second uh forious
accident I think it was an accident
again I'm making up the history as I go
along but it's it's close to the truth
uh he happened to have a magnet in the
laboratory and for some reason the
magnet was in a position here where a
magnetic field was created near where
these particles were being ejected and
what happened when he put the magnetic
field when he put the magnet near this
is the beam split into three separate
beams three separate
beams one went straight ahead
just as if the magnetic field was not
there one of them got deviated to the
left and one of them got deviated to the
right left right right left whatever one
deviated more than the other in fact
they were not
symmetric and Beckel or somebody whoever
was around knew enough to realize that
beams of particles trajectories of
particles get bent by magnetic forces if
you have a magnet and you have a Charged
particle the charged particle goes
through the magnetic field and either
bends to the right or to the left
depending on the sign of the magnetic
field and the charge of the particle so
if the particle was a positively charged
particle it would bend one way in the
magnetic field if it was a negatively
charged particle it would bend the other
way in the magnetic field and what
Beckel had found is that there were
three kinds of radiation one behaving as
if it was composed of electrically
neutral
particles which one was electrically
neutral the one that wasn't deviated at
all course he didn't know they were
particles all he knew is that some
columnated effect happened that
illuminated the uh the uh the detector
the screen the the photographic plate
one of them got deviated to the right as
if it were a negatively charged
particle he called that component of the
radiation he called that component beta
the component that went straight ahead
he called
gamma and the component that deviated in
the other direction as if it were
positively charged he called
Alpha these became the three distinct
kinds of radioactive
um effects three distinct kinds of
radioactivity beta radioactivity gamma
radio gamma and
Alpha just again I'm not interested in
making suspense here let me just tell
you what they were you probably know
what they were many most of you well
many of you know what they were beta was
electrons negatively charged
particles uh which were just the
electrons that already been been
previously discovered from cathode Ray
tubes and that kind of thing these were
electrons coming
out the alpha particles We Now
understand and at that time there was no
precedent for it that they are helium
nuclei two protons and two neutrons
stuck together atomic number
four uh Dalton would have had he had he
had access to helium which he didn't he
would have said helium was number four
on his uh on his um integer collection
of materials and Gamma are photons okay
electrically neutral no electricity at
all and uh these three kinds of
now
um I think he did again I I I don't
remember the history but he might
have had a sufficiently dilute
source that these particles arve d one
at a time at their
destination in that case he would not
have seen a bright spot over here he
would have
seen BLiP BLiP BLiP BLiP illumination
occurring or spots occurring discret
little spots occurring for the
electrons and he might have said oh
those are
particles particles arriving one at a
time Illuminating the screen
discreetly he would have done exactly
the same thing for the alpha particles
he would have found that the alpha
particles arrived one at a time in other
words he could have used he might have
used I probably did used the screen here
as a counter analogous to a guer counter
or something whether he did or not I
don't know uh but um but it's something
you can imagine that he detected the
particles coming one at a time that
would certainly be feas visible with a
Geer
counter and
so evidence that whatever this radiation
is it's coming in discret little bundles
that we could call particles what about
Gamma same thing for gamma gamma's
coming one at a time but at that time
Beckel had no idea neither did anybody
else uh what gamma was it was uncharged
that was all that was
known and it illuminated
uh the
screen just as the others did okay that
was as I said in some sense the first
particle physics experiment we'll come
to some later particle physics
experiment soon
enough all let's next talk about
electromagnetic radiation ordinary
electromagnetic radiation oh well I said
I wasn't going to make suspense gamma is
photons gamma is light gamma well it's
very high energy light but gamma is in
some way connected to ordinary
light so let's come to light gamma was
the big mystery because there were no
neutral particles known at that time
that uh could account for the gamma
radiation and so gamma was a mystery and
that mystery persisted until fairly uh
uh fairly late in the very early 20th
century let's put it that way fairly
late in the very early 20th
century uh was of course plunk and
Einstein really
Einstein who were the first to
understand understand that light comes
in quanta that light comes in photons
but let's go back light was sort of
the strong strong case for something
which was not made of particles light
was something which was clearly made of
fields it was made of the
electromagnetic field okay the
electromagnetic field electric fields
and magnetic fields forming waves when
you shake a charge waves get given off
the wave fields are continuous wave
fields at least according to classical
electrodynamics and they give off waves
that propagate through space completely
continuously and uh Newton of course had
thought that light was uh was particles
but Newton by that time had been
completely uh relegated to the dust bin
at least as far as theory of light went
there were many experiments some of them
done by Newton himself that strongly
said light is waves not not particles so
let's just talk about light a little bit
electromagnetic
radiation if you take electromagnetic
radiation it comes in waves so if
there's a source of electromagnetic
radiation here an antenna some form of
antenna emitting could be radio waves it
could be microwaves it could be uh
infrared it could be light it could be
ultraviolet an atom is a perfectly good
uh antenna incidentally doesn't have to
be a big macroscopic tower an atom with
a charge going around in a circle is an
antenna antennas emit waves
and those electromagnetic waves when
they also fall on a photographic plate
or other device which is sensitive to
light or sensitive to radiation will
illuminate that uh will illuminate that
and turn it white or black turn it black
I guess uh and that's in the character
of light now how do we know that these
things are waves how can we tell that
they're also not bullets shot out of uh
shot out
of uh the source here so one thing you
might
do is do very something very similar to
what was done over here put an
obstruction little hole and see whether
the light is columnated exactly as if it
were bullets being shot out of the gun
here it was bullets you would illuminate
a little spot over here and of course
what happens
is that you don't illuminate such a
small spot you illuminate something
which is fuzzier than
that you eliminate a funny fuzzy region
but that in itself did not prove that
light was waves not at all you could say
well just maybe when these particles go
through this opening here maybe they
have little forces exerted on them by
the edges of the hole here or whatever
which deflect them some of them get
deflected and so maybe you get a more
smear picture a more smearing image than
you might have hoped for so it was not
just that the beams got deflected the
light beams got deflected that in itself
was not enough to argue for uh for a
particle structure to light or sorry a
wave structure to light I'm sorry but
you do something else which is much more
sensitive to the wave character of light
you here's here's the screen over here
again you open up two little holes two
little holes next to each
other if light was simply particles what
you would expect to find here is
basically two smears of the same kind
just superimposed on top of each other
maybe a little extra dense in the center
where they overlap but just two smears
one the image of this hole one the image
of that hole with nothing
unusual okay this of course is not not
what happens what happens is each hole
emits
waves you could do the same trick with
water waves in fact it's not hard to do
the same trick with water
waves and the water waves
interfere if this is the high point of a
wave coming out of here and this is the
low point of a wave places where the
high points combine from the two holes
re enforce each other places where a
high point from one hole meets a low
point from the other hole cancel each
other and so the effect is to see when
it hits the screen here to see
bands bands of positive reinforcement
where the high
points add missing places with no light
where the high points meet low points
right that's an interference pattern
interference pattern is a real signal of
wav like motion of wave Behavior waves
you can do this as I said with water you
just to put your finger into water and
Wiggle two fingers and the two waves
from the two will will spread out some
places they'll reinforce some places
they'll
cancel and so rather peculiarly but not
nothing terribly
unusual um places which were would have
been illuminated by either of the two
holes by themselves there's destructive
interference they get canceled and
places you get constructive interference
and they add and you get extra
intensity that is the kind of thing this
interference property was the kind of
thing that really nailed the wave theory
of
light okay so light was a wave in fact
uh this did not occur after Newton it
really occurred before Newton hyen hin
was
a uh 17th 17th century hin must have
been 17th century but previous to newon
1808 who what Thomas Young yeah the
physicist demonstrated the interference
yeah yeah but but Hans already had the
basic ideas of wave propagation and
that's from the 1600s sometime so this
debate went back and Newton had done
many experiments himself which should
have been interpreted as uh as interfer
as interference wave interference but he
didn't in any
case
after these experiments Young's
experiment others it was definitely
confirmed that light is made of waves
okay what kind of waves Well that took
Maxwell Maxwell realized that they were
waves of electric and magnetic field you
know what an electric and magnetic field
is an electric field well
I look it up if you don't know electric
and magnetic fields and light is a wavy
motion of electric and magnetic fields
first of all light is a wave and here's
a wave moving down the
axis what is that wave a wave
in well it's a wave of electric field
here the electric field is pointing
down here the way electric field is
pointing
up here the electric field is pointing
down let's just draw a line through
there alternating electric field up down
up down and the whole thing moves off
with the speed of light the whole thing
moves off with a speed of light electric
field incidentally there's also a
magnetic field attached to the thing
it's a complicated uh
object it has magnetic field also the
magnetic field is perpendicular to the
the electric field and soort of sticks
out this
way and that's what a light wave would
look like if you could see if you could
sample its electric and magnetic field
as it went past
you of course as it passes you it will
constantly alternate very rapidly if
it's uh if it's a ordinary light wave
much too rapidly for you'd be able to
see but if it were an extremely long
radio wave very very long radio wave you
might be able to see the field
oscillating in front of you and uh this
is this is as I said what it would look
like it's a wave being a wave it will
exhibit interference
patterns and
uh Maxwell had absolutely nailed the
wave and the electromagnetic theory of
light so let's talk about waves a little
bit before
we uh before we talk about about
particles let's talk a little more about
waves and the properties of waves the
first property of a wave that I want
to come to is the wavelength wavelength
is simply the distance along the
wave before you return through before
you return one full cycle to the next
wave all right so you start here and you
go and you come back back to the same
exact kind of thing as over here that's
one cycle or one full wavelength and the
wavelength for symbol for wavelength is
Lambda Greek
Lambda okay Lambda for
length that's the wavelength and it's
measured in uh units of distance it's
measured in meters or it's measured in
centimeters whatever your choice of
units
are
uh okay so Lambda equals wav length
wavelength let's just call it wavelength
another property is if you were to stand
still and just watch the wave go past
you you go head we go up and down and up
and down and up and down it would have
some frequency how many cycles per
second this is not the length of the
wave in space it's kind of the number of
cycles per second or perhaps even
something simpler the time that it takes
to go through one cycle as it passes you
that could be called the period of the
wave
period it's a time it's measured in
seconds so a very and a light wave has a
very very short period up and down and
up and down extremely fast 10 Theus 15th
seconds or something whatever the longer
the wavelength the slower the period the
shorter the wavelength the uh the faster
the the shorter the shorter the
wavelength the shorter the period okay
what's the connection between wavelength
and period okay yeah right so think
about the wave moving past you one
wavelength how long how far does it
moved it's moved distance Lambda how
long has it taken it's taken the
period the distance that it moves
divided by the time that it takes to
move that distance is the velocity of
the wave for light that would be the
speed of light if it's not a light wave
it might be moving with different speed
if it's a water wave it would be much
smaller speed if it's a sound wave if
it's a smaller speed but for a light
wave the wavelength divided by the
period is always equal to the speed of
light whatever the wavelength is the
period is given in terms of the
wavelength or the wavelength is given in
terms of the period so that's a
fundamental relation it's usually
expressed a different
way the inverse of the period one over
the period is called the frequency it's
the number of waves it's the number of
oscillations per second the number of
oscillations per unit time is called the
frequency and that's equal to 1 over the
period faster the period the shorter the
frequency and so you can also write this
as the wavelength times the frequency is
equal to the speed of
light so if I give you the wavelength
you can tell me the frequency if I give
you the frequency you can tell me the
wavelength by solving this
equation and that's the fundamental
connection between wavelength and
frequency now since one of the things
that I really do want to teach you a
little bit is the terminology that
physicists use for things and they tend
not to use the terminology of cycles per
second for frequency they use something
else it's radians per second what does
that mean imagine
a thing going around in a
circle it's going around in a circle
with a frequency F that means F times
around the circle per
second physicists tend to use physicists
and mathematicians tend to use not the
number of times you go around in a
second but the number of radians radian
is about
57° it's an angle about that big how
many radians per second
and the relationship between the
frequency in terms of cycles per second
and the frequency in terms of radians
per second is very simple in terms of
radians per second we call it
Omega ome and they they're closely
connected to each other Omega is just 2
pi times the frequency why 2 pi because
there are 2 pi radians in a circle so
frequency can be measured in either
either way physicists tend to use
Omega except when they're writing
Elementary physics books for
undergraduate premid majors in which
case they use f okay uh we're all
physicists we're all grownup we're all
uh you know so we can use Omega like uh
the world of physics does
Omega is the frequency of the light
measured not in cycles per second but in
radians per second you say where is the
angle for a light wave going don't worry
about where the angle is just divide
frequency or just multiply frequency by
2 pi and that defines Omega right
they're proportional to each other right
so we can also write this then as
uh let's write it this way frequency I'm
going to write it frequency is equal to
C divided by
Lambda and now I'm going to substitute
for frequency Omega / by 2
pi and what do we get we get Omega is
equal to 2 pi C over
Lambda fundamental equation of wave
motion that the frequency measured in
radians and the wavelength are related
by 2 pi times the speed of light this of
course is true for any wave if you plug
in the right
velocity okay we will use that equation
from time to time so
get it down
now as I said light comes in different
wavelengths and those different
wavelengths characterize the different
kinds of
radiation radio waves are very long
wavelengths meters are certainly more
than uh certainly more than uh uh
microscopic lengths radio waves can be
anything from what a few cenm to uh 10
cm something I don't remember exactly
where the radio spectrum
begins
hm no it can go up to
anything arbitrarily long wavelengths
are called still radio waves even though
no radio could work on the basis of
waves that had a wavelength of a billion
light years but still they're still call
radio
waves um and where where's the smaller
what's the smallest radio wave I think
about 10 cm I all right small and it's a
highly arbitrary division of course
completely arbitrary what's smaller than
radio waves smaller
wavelength microwaves microwaves go from
a few centimeters down to what the micro
micrometer or something like that
Micron uh smaller wavelength than
microwaves infrared infrared waves and
then from infrared waves you have light
waves visible light visible light is a
rather narrow range of frequencies or
wavelengths and then comes uh
ultraviolet shorter
wavelengths X-rays and gamma rays gamma
rays are just exactly these objects here
very very short wavelength extremely
short wavelength uh radiation and that's
what the Beckel had discovered coming
out of
there the only trouble
is that Beckel discovered discret bumps
you know discret blips one at a time and
not nice
continuous
waves okay that then brings us to the
puzzle of quantum mechanics now we're
not going to go into it in any great
depth certainly not tonight but let's
just recount the history a little
bit Einstein and plank realized for a
variety of reasons mostly thermodynamic
properties of light
that Einstein that light had to be
thought of as being made up out of
discret indivisible
elements uh he might have it might have
been an experimental Discovery in fact
in some sense beckel's Discovery was an
experimental Discovery it's just he
didn't realize the thing he was seeing
was electromagnetic radiation so I won't
go through the actual history but let's
make up a imaginary history of how the
discreetness of light might have been
discovered it could have been discovered
this
way you again shine your
light on a you shine your light on a
screen and you illuminate the screen and
of course what you see is a nice
continuous blob of light it could either
be an interference pattern or it could
just be a single hole in which case it
would just be a blob on the
screen okay
but now you do the experiment
differently here's your source of light
you put an obstruction in the way the
obstruction is a is a filter the
obstruction is a not a filter but a um a
semi-transparent uh semi-opaque
thing which blocks out a certain
percentage of the light what happens
over here well the blob gets dimmer okay
it's not as intense you make it thicker
it's even less intense you see less
light AR ding per unit of time and you
make it even a little bit thicker and at
some point all of a sudden the character
of what's here
changes and instead of seeing the blob
you see the
screet events little blips now if you
wait a long time these little blips
build
up and they build up to something which
has exactly the same
pattern as the blob had so the blob in
this case then is some sort of effect
that has to do with lots of little blips
so many little blips that you can't
recognize them as being
individual that's the blob but if you
attenuate the light and cut it down so
that the intensity coming through here
is really really small what you see is
blips this experiment can actually be
done it was not done in those early days
but you can imagine and this is what
Einstein had suggested really does
happen in his photoelectric paper that
light comes through as absolutely
discret things the motivation for it was
was uh thermodynamics and other things
but this might have been the form of
Discovery discovering these individual
blips on the screen and this is what
really would happen so something very
very confusing going
on light is a wave that had already been
proved in fact if
we put a screen over here with two
little holes in
it two little holes in it we will again
see light coming
through bit by
bit
one at a
time and if we leave it up there a long
time the
blips will sort of fill
in and what they will form is an
interference
pattern so it became clear that there
clear but still very confusing that
light is made up out of indivisible
elements called
photons and that the wave character of
of the light really represents or the
wave pattern really represents the
probability that the photon appears at
different places in other words it's
randomly arriving blips but they arrive
with a probability in different
locations which
follows the pattern that was established
by the wave theory the wave theory gives
you a wave theory of
probabilities that's quantum mechanics
we made have to talk about we will have
to talk about quantum mechanics a great
deal
more um
but this kind of experiment this kind of
observation about light was the first
example of a connection which is really
in a sense what this course is all
about it's a connection first of all
between waves of any
kind
and particles they are not two different
things somehow waves and particles are
two manifestations of the same thing
we'll have to come back to that and
we'll try to explain it perhaps again
later now I'm just filling in some early
early
facts uh mostly just to set the
stage w aves some particles at least
when it came to
light were Were Somehow intimately
connected and it didn't make sense to
say light is a particle or it didn't
make sense to say light is a wave uh but
has manifestations of both all right the
situation only got more
complicated
when electrons was studied electrons are
clearly particles everybody knows
electrons are particles there was no
ambiguity about that no more ambiguity
than there was about whether light was a
wave or not it was but yet something
funny well something funny also happened
with electrons you could do exactly the
same kind of experiment with electrons
you can today this experiment can really
be
done
uh at the time it was a bit of a thought
experiment but equivalent experiments
You' have to put the holes you have to
make a screen you put the holes much
closer to each other if you want do it
with electrons for one reason or another
and you send electrons through of course
they come through one at a time
everybody knew electrons were little
particles that came through one at a
time but was totally unexpected is or
would have been unexpected was that the
electrons when you open two
holes form an interference
pattern so it wasn't just that light was
funny particles were funny in
general uh
electrons exhibited wave properties
light ex exhibited particle properties
in fact had we taken the alpha particles
which are much heavier than electrons
much much heavier than electrons 8,000
times heavier than an electron much
harder to do these kind of experiments
with but send them through two little
holes like that we also would see
interference patterns this has been done
with objects which are much much bigger
than helium nuclei namely Bucky Balls
Bucky Balls have been sent through uh uh
interference experiments like this and
seen to form the same kind of
interference pattern so everybody know
what a bucky ball is 60
carbon 60
uh in the shape of a soccer ball in
shape of a a generalized soccer ball
yeah right uh is it is it a regular is
is a regular soccer ball got six yeah
like a soccer ball no it's not it's not
really a soccer ball but
uh
so and is widely believe that if you did
it with bowling balls well you can't
really do it with bowling balls much
much much too hard I understand that
people who did it with Bucky Balls are
going to try to do it with living cells
viruses to prove the
viruses are quantum
mechanical and then they're going to ask
the
virus what the virus felt
it
anyway
good the waves and particles are somehow
the same thing and if you want to
penetrate that more deeply you got to
learn some quantum mechanics and the
place to do it is
um in my lectures which don't cost
anything they're on the
internet okay that's uh now let's talk
about the properties of photons a little
bit photons are these discrete
indivisible elements of
light light has
energy if you absorb the
sunlight it Heats things obviously has
energy so therefore photons have
energy what do we know about the en of a
photon photons being indivisible we know
the energy must come in very discret
packets now what is a photon
characterized by or a light wave imagine
a light wave coming in
composed out of these discrete photons
don't try to picture it it's impossible
to picture when the light wave actually
falls on a screen it forms these little
dots so it's
particles made of particles but we see
some some sort of wave phenomena
associated with it the wave phenomena is
associated with a wavelength and
therefore a frequency an angular
frequency we discover that that light
wave is made up out of discrete units
each with an indivisible bit of energy
cannot be subdivided and the energy of
one
Photon the energy of every single Photon
in this light beam with a given
wavelength and a given frequency is
given by a number called H bar Plank's
constant one of Plank's many one of one
of plunks
constants H Bar times
Omega in other
words Omega is large when the wavelength
is short the shorter the wavelength the
larger the
frequency the larger the frequency or
the shorter the wavelength the larger
the energy in every
Photon so first lesson short wavelength
photons have lots of energy long
wavelength individual photons have very
low energy now of course a radio wave
can carry a huge amount of energy
there's no question you can make radio
waves with lots and lots of
energy how do you make way radio waves
with lots of energy you pile lots of
photons up many many photons
all with the same wavelength and the
same
frequency but there is something
nevertheless some remnant of the
discreetness namely the energy of such a
wave is always an integer
multiple this is the energy of a
photon the energy of a light Ray let's
just call it a ray or a light wave is
some inte number as an integer multiple
of H
Omega right so the light rays come in
indivisible units every light Ray Every
Light W every pulse of light with a
given frequency and uh wave wave
wavelength has an integer multiple of
energy in units of H bar
Omega all right so this is an important
equation here this equation is of of
absolute
Central importance to understanding why
particle physics is the way it is in
particular it's very very Central to the
question of why we have to build big
giant machines to see smaller and
smaller
objects uh my grandson my grandson's not
a kid he's 26 years old but he asked me
one day how come you have to build
bigger and bigger machines to see
smaller and smaller things why don't you
build small machines to see all right
we're going to try to answer that
question but this is the central fact
that the energy is
proportional to the frequency of a phot
of a given of a single
Photon
um all right we've been through waves
and particles photons being carrying
discrete units of
energy I want to come to another set of
Concepts now this
is we're not we're certainly not
abandoning this line of thought here but
there's another line of thought that I
want to remind you of mostly remind you
of not quantum mechanics but the special
theory of
relativity special theory of relativity
plays a very important role in particle
physics particle physics is in a sense
relativistic quantum mechanics the
combination of Relativity and quantum
mechanics and so let me just remind you
of one particular simple fact and then
be clear about what that fact
means most famous equation of physics
eal
mc^2 this equation also plays a very
important role in the reason that
for in explaining why particle physics
is the way it
is energy is mc^ squ let's just be very
clear about what it
means um in the early days of Relativity
people spoke of the rest mass of a
object and the moving mass of an object
the moving mass and the rest Mass were
different mass of an object was minimum
when it was standing still but when it
moved the mass
increases you still read that in
elementary physics textbooks but you
never read it in any uh in any
um work of modern physics you never read
that the mass of an object depends on
its state of
motion it's largely a change in
language the change in language is such
that what we now call mass is what used
to be called rest Mass period whenever I
refer to a mass of an object I'm talking
about its rest
Mass all electrons have exactly the same
rest
mass period if you look up the masses of
particles in a uh in a you know in a
table of masses and so forth you will
not find them called rest Mass you will
just call find them called Mass so from
now on we will never speak about the
rest Mass we will speak about the mass
of the electron as a number that
experimental physicists measure in great
detail every electron has exactly the
same mass as every other electron and
the mass is not something which depends
on the state of
motion but of course the energy is
something which depends on the state of
motion the faster an electron moves the
more kinetic energy it
has so there's something wrong with this
equation yes there's something wrong
with this equation this equation is no
longer even though it's the most famous
equation in physics it's not the right
equation at least with modern
terminology energy is only equal to mass
time c^ 2 for an object at
rest the right way to say it is the
energy of an object at
rest if the object has no nit motion now
it could be a complicated object with
all sorts of internal motions but but it
could be a box of gas all the molecules
flying around like mad but as long as
the box of gas is itself stationary then
we speak of its rest mass and we can
speak of its rest energy the energy of
that box of gas when it's standing still
and Einstein's equation says that the
rest energy of an object is the rest
mass or just the mass times the speed of
light squared now what exactly let me
imagine two experiments that you might
do to confirm this
just to understand precisely what it
means you take a
pot
of not a pot a box with molecules in
it and you put it on a scale to measure
its weight or its
mass draw a
scale the molecules are cold you begin
with the box of gas very very cold and
you measure the mass sorry you measure
yes you measure the mass you get some
number now you feed some energy into the
box you heat it up you heat up the
molecules in here you increase their
energy the box is still at rest the
molecules are not the molecules are
moving around but the boxes at rest and
we can ask what is the rest mass of the
box of gas
the answer is if you increase the energy
by adding thermal energy you add a
certain number of calories or a certain
number of jewels jewel is a unit of
energy to the Box you will discover that
the box is mass the box of gas its mass
increases its weight
increases okay now the amount that it
would increase is so
tiny if you increase the temperature by
1,000° or something it's so tiny that it
would be quite
unmeasurable but in principle this is
the meaning of eal mc^2 an object at
rest if you add energy to it its mass
increases its weight increases also its
inertia increases harder to move
it okay another example now this is the
this example is not something that you
can really do but the other example is
something that is you know real
experimental physics observational
physics you start not you start with an
electron and a
positron we haven't talked about
antiparticles let's just uh ignore the
fact that we haven't talked about them
for a moment two kinds of particles
electrons which have negative charge
positrons which have positive charge
they have exactly the same mass
precisely the same mass they are in
every respect similar except for the
fact that they have oppos opposite
electric charge because they have
opposite electric charge they can
combine and disappear they have plus
charge and a minus charge the net charge
is zero nothing prevents them from
disappearing while something does
prevent them from
disappearing they have energy each one
has an energy let's suppose these two
particles are at rest we bring them
together each one has an energy equal to
mc^
2 so the total energy is twice
mc
squ mc squ for each particle we bring
them together that energy can't
disappear energy is conserved what
happens to that
energy that energy becomes photons
photons go out you bring an electron
next to a positron and you let them
annihilate poof out go photons the
photons in some sense are energy they
can be absorbed by a material and heat
the
material they they can be converted to
all forms of
energy and how much energy do you get by
annihilating an electron and a positron
the answer is twice the mass of an
electron times the speed of light
squared it's a tiny amount of energy I
mean if you just had one electron and
positron you couldn't do much with
it you need uh you know huge numbers of
them to to heat a cup of coffee but uh
but still in principle that's what
happens and of course this is this is an
observational
fact that's the meaning ofal mc^2 and
another way to really say it which I
think is the right way to say it is to
say energy and mass at least for an
object at rest are the same thing why do
we have to have an equation really it's
just a conversion of units from what we
call mass units to what we call Energy
units and this tells you the conversion
roughly like a
conversion from meters to uh to
centimeters or
whatever this is the conversion between
energy units and mass
units right but any case if you know the
mass of an object and you want to know
how much energy you would get if it
disappeared you multiply by the square
of the speed of light so you get a lot
of energy for a small amount of
mass what is a speed of light and what
is pl's constant
let's write down the numerical values of
the speed of light and pl's
constant we need them one for here and
one
for for here Photon energy underc squ is
does the
mass have to have a mechanism for the
energy to be released or
well does it have yes it has to have a
mechanism
and we haven't talked about that
mechanism but just let's let's stand on
the outside and say look this thing
happens an electron and a positron when
you put them together will just
disappear let's not ask what the
mechanism is the one thing we know is
independent of the mechanism energy
should be
conserved if E equals mc^2 for the
electrons that energy has to show up
somewhere so there are some things you
say without knowing what the mechanism
is conservation laws where you know that
certain things are conserved you can
often
say important things about a system
without knowing detailed
mechanisms okay let's talk about uh
numbers the speed of light is a very big
number Plank's constant is a very small
number how do I know it's a small number
well the energy of a photon is a tiny
amount of energy the frequency of a
light wave is very large so it better be
that H bar is a small number let's write
them down okay so C the speed of light
that is equal to
458 I I'm not kidding you this is true
plus or minus something in the last
digit over here time 10
8 m per
second units units are important it's
not just 2.99 762 458 * 10 8 it's that
number of meters per second that's a
speed of light how about Plank's
constant I I everybody of course will
memorize this number
because it's important to this class
that you know that
number one point same thing here
memorize this one 1.05 455
1628 * 10-
34 very small number and what are the
units anybody know what the units are I
worked out the units but I I think I
erased
them
H energy times time
right but what are the units of
energy mass time velocity squared right
MC squ better be MC squ mass time
velocity mass
kilog time length squar over time squar
that's energy and plun constant has
another unit of uh length in it another
unit of
time okay so Plank's constant is
measured
in what's the unit of
mass kilograms
kilogram me
squared
divided by
seconds so why are these numbers so
crazy why are they so big why are they
so small why are they so odd I mean
couldn't was nature playing some awful
joke on us to put these that to make
these numbers so
awkward
uh or are people just being foolish in
using peculiar
units for example the speed of light
is something which depends on your
choice of units if you measure it
instead of measuring it in me/ second
you measure it in feet per hours you
will get a different
answer so there's nothing sacred about
this number it depends on your choice of
units length units in this case and time
units you could certainly work with
units in which the speed of light was a
more convenient
number you could work with units in
which the speed of light was one the
units would be light years per year for
example the speed of light is one
lightyear per year or one light second
per second so it's not hard to choose
the speed of light to be one you just
use different units of space and time
same is true of Plank's constant you can
use units in which Plank's constant is
equal to
one but why is it that we actually use
such peculiar units
why don't how come the people who
invented units Mr metric or whoever he
was the the British are worse in the
metric system of course they were really
perverse
5,280 feet in a
mile how many um how many Stone how many
pounds in a
stone
16 I don't know where they got these
units from H I don't know was a St own
16 lb I can't 14 lb even
worse 16 is at least divisible by two
four times but okay 14 14 pound high is
yourse H how many hands high is your
horse that's another good one how about
horsepower yeah I mean just bizarre
units metric units are better but
they're also very very arbitrary for
example the meter had to do with how far
a man's hand is from his nose why CU he
was using measuring length of rope or
something
uh so these are highly arbitrary units
and have more to do with Biology than
they have to do with physics they have
to do with Biology in the sense that the
real question is not
why uh a meter is what it is why why a
meter is what it is it's a question of
why why an arm has to have X number of
molec ules in
it and there's nothing special about
these numbers all right given that you
can ask are there units are there better
choices of units of the three units what
do we need we have we need three units
we need a
length the three things that need the
three kinds of units we need are
length meters or feet or
whatever
time
seconds or years or hours or something
else and
mass all of the other units in physics
can be reexpressed in terms of these
this is a complete set of uh of units
there are three of them and we can
choose them in various ways for example
instead of using the kilogram we could
use the mass of a proton as the basic
unit of mass or the mass of a of the Sun
or and so forth use different units of
mass
um certain things in astrophysics are a
lot easier not easier but a lot the
small the equations are simpler they
involve less constants fewer constants
if you use units in which the mass of
the Sun is
one okay uh equations in nuclear
physics are simpler only simpler in the
sense that they don't involve as many
arbitrary constants if you use units in
which the mass of a proton is
one so you can make your equation
simpler and get rid of these weird
numbers and how many numbers can you get
rid of how many numbers can you get rid
of this well you have a choice of three
units Mass length and time and that
means you can simplify three of the
constants of nature or three of the of
these type of constants
here uh and set them equal to one if you
like so
in astrophysics or in cosmology you
might want to use the Lightyear that's a
much better unit than the
centimeter and if you use the Lighty
year and also the year Lighty year for
distance year for time speed of light
comes out one of course so we can
simplify
three numbers
usually and what do we so the question
of which numbers we simplify might
depend on what kind of physics we're
doing if we're doing astrophysics we
might want to simplify certain numbers
if we're doing Atomic physics we might
want to simplify other
numbers
um and in particle
physics in particle
physics there
are basically these two
constants which we can set equal to one
by appropriate choices of
units appropriate choices of units can
set c equal to 1 that's easy you just
use units in which time is
measured uh in such a way that time and
distance are measured in such a way that
the distance something moves in one unit
of time is one unit of
distance you can also set H bar equal to
one
and you have your choice about one other
unit what's a good unit to set equal to
one what's a good unit to a mass unit to
set equal to one in particle
physics well you could use what about
the proton why not the proton or why not
the higs BOS on or why not the uh why
not the the uh the me particle or well
the answer is obvious that there isn't
the best there is no particularly good
unit of Mass which will simplify
particle physics so that the at best you
could at best you can set one arbitrary
particle to have a mass of
one and uh that would be foolish because
there would be no particular reason to
focus on any one particle what about the
why do we pick the speed of light and
plunk constant as equations they appear
in so many equations well they do appear
in so many equations but so does the
mass of the proton
or the or the size of the proton why
uh okay I'll tell you
why uh there are two very very
fundamental facts about plunk constant
and the speed of light and the way that
I'll say it is just to say the
words no object in nature moves faster
than the speed of light it doesn't
matter what it is no matter how you try
to accelerate it you can get it up
closer and closer to the speed of light
but you can't pass the speed of light
right for any object in nature any right
so there's something Universal about the
speed of light it's a universal bound
Universal for all forms of matter for
anything that we can make it has a
certain
universality all objects are constrained
by the speed of
light so it has some uh it has some
reason to be thought of as something
Universal what about Plank's constant
does plun constant come into anything
where you would want to say everything
in the world necessarily has precisely
this
property it's the uncertainty principle
we haven't discussed the uncertainty
principle but all objects in nature the
Precision with which you can measure
their positions and velocities and
momenta are constrained by exactly the
same constant the uncertainty in
position times the uncertainty in
momentum are always constrained to be as
big or bigger than Plank's constant
again everything all particles not just
particles but objects of all kind are
constrained by the same
number so it's for that reason the
specialness of these two constants that
it makes a lot of sense to set them
equal to
one the size of the proton for example
or not the size of the pro well let's
say the size of the proton or the mass
of the proton there's nothing nothing
very special about the proton the proton
is one of hundreds of elementary
elementary one of hundreds of objects uh
why didn't we set the mass of um uh give
me some weird element from up there um
rubidium why didn't we set the mass of a
rubidium atom to one because you say
rubidium is not in any way more special
than um
fonum okay you're learning about my uh
chemistry knowledge okay there's nothing
special about ridium it's just one of
many same thing is true of the proton
it's just one of many the electron is
one of many so there's nothing Universal
about it is there a third Universal
quantity which is so special that we
might want to set it equal to one
something which everything is
constrained
by yeah the trouble is electric charge
is a dimensionless quantity but yes we
could uh the the electric charge is a
fundamental constant like that gravity
gravity right what can we say we can say
all objects in
nature attract each other with a force
which is equal to the product of the
mass divided by the square of the
distance between them times Newton's
constant we don't make any
exceptions it's not that there are some
objects which do that and other objects
St incidentally in the case of the
electric charge of course there are
neutral particles so not all objects
interact in the same way electrically
but everything in the world interacts
exactly the same way product of the
masses divided by the square of the
distance between them times Newton's
constant so Newton's constant is one of
these very Universal
things
G I don't know what is it
6.74 9 8 3 1
54 I assure you it's not known to
anything like that kind of
precision I think it's 6.7 * 10us 11th
in some units or other it's another
thing that it makes a lot of sense to
set equal to one why don't we do it in
particle
physics the reason is that partical
physics is totally insensitive to
gravity the gravity gravitational force
between objects and particle physics is
absolutely
negligible so gravity would be a stupid
thing to set equal to one because
gravity just doesn't come into the
equations of particle physics particles
are too light to experience significant
amounts of gravity particles that we
know about today are just too light to
experience any significant
gravity and so it uh there's no
particular value since none of the
equations in particle physics involve G
it better to leave it alone just go away
and not fix one of the units just leave
it
free isn't it even fair to say that uh
making the assumtion that you're
dismissing it in fact what's that isn't
it fair to say that uh part physics
dismisses it all the time because it
would be insignificant you actually
don't even it's not even fair to assume
that g is dismissible that in fact
you're examining that these high
energies may not be subject to gravity
in the classical way we know well of
course we know that they are subject to
gravity if you take enough particles
they form the Earth and you take another
enough particle apart yeah so that's
that's right we don't really really know
what
uh how Elementary particles
well no we do well we can certainly take
one elementary particle and see how it
behaves in the field of the earth see
whether it falls and they do single
particles do fall in the field of the
Earth but uh how single particles would
influence each other gravitationally
that of course has never been measured
and so yeah it's uh it's possible to
question whether the universal law of
gravitation applies to
particles uh I don't think many
physicists do question it but the main
point is a point a practical point
there's no benefit gotten by setting G
equal to 1 in particle physics because G
just doesn't come into particle physics
at least uh in
current uh versions of particle
physics there are other
attractions such as attractions of two
electrons or the other forces wouldn't
it make sense the you're talking about
gravitational attraction to set those to
one instead of G attraction two
electrons for example electrons don't
attract they repel but yeah um but yeah
you could do that but that doesn't go
into your partical physics either it
does go into your partical
physics right it
does it does
um yes you you could use units and we
often do in which the electric charge is
equal to one and the attraction uh the
repulsion yeah is the third
constant you could for you could you
could you could you could traditionally
we haven't yeah traditionally we haven't
uh there's a reason that we haven't and
I'll we'll we'll eventually get to it
wasn't that your point about electric
charge being dimensionless once once you
set c h to be dimensionless the charge
is also
Dimension uh yeah the charge the charge
is equal to one over 100 the square of
the charge is equal to 1 over 100 137 is
a dimensionless measure of the
charge uh and it's it's a completely
dimensionless
number and um we'll come to it we'll
come to what it means it uh you could
colum's constant is one you're saying
did that be the third one if you didn't
col well you can't set one over 137 you
one there's an obstruction
to because col con actually when I took
physics that's what they did the third
one they said colum's constant who
constant yeah you
could you
could for whatever reason historically
we haven't done that and there's
probably no particular benefit in it
um in any case we will use units in
which C and H bar are equal to one quite
often not always but sometimes only when
want to illustrate the size of numbers
will I put C and H bar back into
equations so
we
uh oh some equations come out very
simpler yeah if we set c equal to 1 then
e is equal to M that's it energy and
energy and mass are just the same thing
we had another equation over here here
e of
a energy for a photon this is the energy
of a massive particle which has some
rest mass energy of a photon is equal to
H Omega well equation simplifies if we
set H H bar equal to one energy is just
equal to
frequency so that uh that's just an
illustration of the use of what's that
frequency M no well yes yes yes yes yes
but not for a photon photons have no
Mass don't forget this is okay there's a
difference between these two the meaning
of e in these equations in this equation
it's rest
mass and rest
energy but photons can never be brought
to rest nevertheless they do have energy
but it's not rest energy it's the it's
basically kinetic energy photons have
kinetic energy uh energy of motion so
this is just plain energy whatever the
energy is and it's equal to their
frequency so they're two different uh
yeah well mass and rest mass and rest
energy are relistic because what is zero
what is
rest it has to be relative to something
yeah yeah no no no just just forget the
word rest now forget the word rest you
just use it to differentiate them but
you know what is mass at rest in the
universe where would it be not in the
universe it's in the laboratory we're
talking about yeah and then then it
becomes relative to the relative to the
laboratory energies are measured
relative to the laboratory energies are
different depending on the state of
motion of the
Observer if you have a photon or
anything else and two different
observers observing it they see two
different energies obviously even even
in Newtonian physics that's true if I
have an object here and I see it I say
it has no kinetic
energy you're running by at 100 miles an
hour you look at it and you see that it
has kinetic energy so energy is
something both side yeah energy is
something that depends on the state of
motion of an object it makes sense to
ask what the energy of this cup of
coffee is when it's at rest then it's
just the internal motion of the molecule
and so forth and um no no overall
kinetic energy that's the thing which is
the m when you write energy is equal to
mass right but all I'm saying is the the
counter that it's sitting on is not
atress what's that in the universe the
counter sitting
on
okay I me if it's at rest then it's rest
relative to something else yes and the
point is is that energy is measured
relative to a given frame of
reference energy is not a universal
thing that everybody will agree
on it's relative to a particular frame
of reference so relative to my frame of
reference the energy of this cup of
coffee when it's standing still relative
to me is equal to its mass
okay earlier this evening again on this
whole subject of uh of of naming things
in constant yeah you didn't like
frequency cycles per second you said
physicist use Omega 2 pi to some extent
that's a historical fact my question is
it seems to me uh 2 pi using radi 57
whatever 2 pi times that is more
complicated than a complete
cycle I agree with you why why would one
use something that appears to be more
complex than the single
side good
question good
question engineering math get simpler if
you do that engineering math yeah yeah I
mean there's some mathematical
Simplicity to radians that the this
uh I I think the answer is you look at
all the equations you write down you
write them in both terms of frequencies
and you write them in terms of
omegas and you see in which form do you
encounter fewer factors of 2
pi I'm not sure what the answer to that
is uh Omega Omega for sure it's simpler
you think so oh
yeah yeah you do a lot of things with e
to the ey
something practically speaking is it
possible to accelerate two
particles fast enough with energy that
they will interact
gravitation in principle certainly
practically speaking
large very far from
it very very far from
it
no of course it depends on what you mean
by a particle I don't think you'd want
to call the earth a
particle but uh
no well what's
Elementary yeah yeah what is the source
of
positron what say a source of positron
what is a source of positrons high
energy
collisions that's the only way to do it
you need yeah you need a you need a
collision to uh to create positrons
nuclear yeah nuclear processes
sorry nuclear Decay sometimes you
we used the planks con uh plank time and
plank distance and things like that well
we're not doing that plank time and
plank distance correspond to setting G
equal to one okay yeah so we're not
doing that now the one of the reasons
that we might might not want to do that
is once you set three of these equal
to one let's say then you have a natural
unit of length a natural unit of time
and a natural unit of mass the natural
unit of length when you said G equal to
1 and all of them equal to one is called
the plunk length and it's very very much
smaller than anything that comes up in
normal particle physics so you would not
want to measure particle
sizes particle radi and so forth in
units of the plunk M plunk length it's
just too small it's much smaller than
anything that occurs in so that's the
reason for not doing
it you you would use it like in black
holes or cosmology yeah and anything
that really involves gravity and quantum
mechanics together and relativity it
makes sense to put all three of them to
one uh but if only two of them are
important you may only want to set two
of the constants equal to one okay um
let's see I want to go a little bit F
further yeah let's go a little bit
further with the basic
Concepts that we'll draw on over and
over I mean today I'm just listing
basically the preliminary
Concepts practically establishing uh
language energy
Mass
particles
waves
Fields let's talk talk about another
concept that comes up over and over in
particle physics in fact it comes up
over and over in almost all physics
momentum momentum if you take an object
and it's at rest it has no momentum at
all it may have energy it has eal mc^
squ energy but it has no momentum an
object at
rest if it's moving it typically has
momentum momentum is concerned D just
like energy when two objects hit each
other the net amount of momentum doesn't
change right so momentum is a conserved
quantity and because it's a conserved
quantity it has an importance
uh anything that's conserved is
important momentum is a combination of
the mass of an object or better yet its
rest its energy its energy and its
direction of motion its mass its
velocity and its direction of motion
it's a vector quantity it's a vector
quantity and as a rule it's proportional
or it's as a vector quantity it points
along the direction of motion of an
object points along its velocity for a
non-relativistic object an object moving
with much slower than the speed of
light the
momentum of course is equal to the
mass times the velocity the arrow on top
means that it's a vector quantity it has
a
direction okay so mass time velocity is
momentum in non-relativistic physics but
it's not quite the right expression for
in relativistic physics and in
particular it's not quite the right
thing for things moving with the speed
of
light so let's talk about light does
light have first of all does light have
energy yes a beam of light shining on
something Heats it does light have
momentum now ordinary light if it hits
you in the chest or something doesn't
give you much of a push why it's because
the the light so dilute and it just
doesn't have much of a kick okay but if
you got hit by this laser beam that they
make in uh where is it in across the bay
on the other side with what's that place
um Livermore yeah they got this great
big laser and Laser shines its light and
when it hits a piece of material it just
implodes it what is it that's imploding
it it's the momentum of the light just
pure sheer momentum and it can be huge
so yes light has momentum and a pulse of
light moving along let's imagine a pulse
of light moving
along the
x-axis every pulse of light moving along
a given Direction now of course real
light might have some dispersion it
might uh some of it might go out some
parts of the light wave may go one way
some parts me go the other way but if
the light is very columnated so it's
moving along a particular axis then the
right formula now I'm not going to prove
this I'm not going to prove it I'm just
going to tell you the right formula for
a light
beam
is that it is the energy of the light
beam divided by the speed of
light let me just compare it with this
or another way to write it is the energy
is C * P but let's leave it in this form
here now let me just compare these two
things momentum is mass times velocity
momentum is energy divided by velocity
just a simple question are they
dimensionally the same are they
dimensionally the same so to inquire
whether they're dimensionally the same
all you have to remember is that the
dimensions of energy are mass times the
speed of light
squar
so just in terms of units energy is like
mc^ squ divided by C just tells you that
the momentum of a beam of light is it's
mass times its
velocity not really it's Mass it's Mass
the rest the mass of a light beam is
really zero it has no Mass rest Mass but
in terms of units it's equal to an
energy * c^ 2 sorry a mass time c^2
divided by C you get the point it's just
a question of
units this doesn't look like this in
terms of units one has a velocity
upstairs one has a velocity downstairs
but it is the same in units when you
remember that E equals mc^2 okay so this
is the
formula for the momentum or the Rel
relationship between the momentum and
the energy of a light
beam and it points in the direction
along the state along the motion that's
right that's right uh how to write this
let's just say the magnitude of the it
points along the direction of the light
beam but the magnitude of the momentum
is equal to the energy divided by C the
magnitude of the momentum the direction
is along the direction of axis of Light
Beam along the state of along the
direction of motion of the light beam
but the magnitude of the momentum the
size of it is equal to the energy of the
light beam divided by the speed of light
C okay you can see now
momentum is energy divided by C that's
why that's why the momentum is so small
you can detect the energy of a light
beam sure you can it heats up uh it
heats up a little bit of water it heats
up it evaporates water and so forth it's
not hard to detect the energy but it's
quite hard to detect the momentum of the
light beam and that's because there's
this C in the denominator here momentum
of a light beam is very small
typically of course if you as I said if
you pump up the light beam enough it can
give quite a
kick all right so that oh oh let's uh
let's do one little
exercise all right let's just um
yeah the momentum of a light beam is its
energy divided by the speed of light now
we had a formula do you remember the
formula for the energy of a photon let's
take one Photon now one photon is an
example of a light beam let's figure out
what the momentum of a photon is so it
is equal to its energy divided by the
speed of light but what's the energy of
a
photon H bar
Omega so the momentum
in magnitude is equal to H Omega divided
by the speed of
light now do you remember the
relationship between
frequency wavelength and the speed of
light we had that
before that yeah what was it the fre
frequency time wavelength is equal to C
right frequency wavelength and now if I
if I put Omega
here uh Omega * Lambda is what 2 pi * C
or 2 Pi / c 2 pi * C right 2 pi *
C No 2
pi C over 2
pi C over 2 pi good C over 2
pi
is that
right wait Omega is bigger than
F Omega is bigger than F right all right
yeah right so wait a minute I I don't
believe you I don't believe you I got to
do it myself I got we have frequency C *
Lambda equal C
right so
therefore yeah
so now wait Omega is equal to 2 pi *
frequency right so frequency is Omega
over 2 pi so this is Omega over 2
pi and I say that Omega * Lambda is 2 pi
* C I was
right
right Omega * Lambda is 2 pi C so let's
get rid of the Omega here and write
Omega is equal to 2 pi C over Lambda
I've just divided by Lambda let's just
see what we get we get momentum of a
photon is
H ided by C and now times Omega and
Omega is 2
pi over Lambda times C the C's cancel
out that's good because I know the C's
should cancel
out and what do we find we find the
momentum of a
photon is 2 pi H bar that's a number
divided by the
wavelength what H what's that yeah yeah
yeah 2 pi H bar equals H right right we
could that's
right right so right so so p is also
equal to just oldfashioned H ided by
Lambda there's an example where we was
POS possibly not so smart to use H
bar right okay look the two pies are
going to get you one way or another
someplace they're going to get you the
pies always come up somewhere you can't
get rid of them okay um what does this
say this says the shorter the wavelength
the larger the momentum of a photon
a a single Photon of a radio wave has a
very very small momentum a single Photon
of a gamma ray a gamma ray is a very
very short wavelength Photon has a good
kick to it one Photon it won't hit it's
still a pretty small kick but what this
is telling you is that the momentum is
related to the wavelength the shorter
the wavelength the bigger the momentum
that is an extremely important lesson
that the shorter the wavelength the
bigger the momentum and also of course
the bigger the energy the energy and the
momentum are related or proportional to
each
other so if you try to make very short
wavelength photons the result will be
that you have to spend a lot of energy
to make them now it becomes clear
why physicists have to build bigger and
bigger machines to see smaller and
smaller things the reason is if you want
to see a small thing you have to use
short
wavelengths if you try to take a picture
of me with radio
waves I would look like a
blur if you wanted to see any sort of
distinctness to my features you would
have to use wavelengths which are
shorter than the size of my head if you
wanted to see
uh um a little hair on my head you would
have to use wavelengths which are as
small as the thickness of the hair on my
head the smaller the object that you
want to see in a
microscope the shorter the wavelength of
light that you have to use okay if you
want to see an atom literally see what's
going on in an atom you have to
illuminate it with radiation whose
wavelength is as short as the size of
the
atom but that means the shorter the
wavelength the smaller the object you
want to see the larger the
momentum of the photons that you would
have to use to see it so if you want to
see really small things you have to use
very make very high energy particles
very high energy photons or very high
energy particles of different
types uh how do you make high energy
particles you accelerate them in bigger
and bigger accelerators you have to pump
more and more energy into them to make
very high energy particles so this
equation and its near relative what is
its near relative E equals H bar
Omega these two equations are sort of
the
central theme of particle
physics that particle physics
progresses by making higher and higher
energy particles because the higher and
higher energy particles have shorter and
shorter wavelength and allow you to see
smaller and smaller
structures that's the pattern that has
held sway over basically A Century of
particle physics or almost a century of
particle
physics uh they're striving for smaller
and smaller distances that's obviously
what you want to do you want to see
smaller and smaller things and at the
same time the striving for shorter and
shorter wavelengths which means either
higher and higher momentum or higher and
higher energy particles theoretical
limit is there a limit to shorter and
shorter yeah we think there is well yes
and no yes in some sense yes we think
when you get down to the plunk length
something new begins to happen and we
can talk about that at some point in
these lectures where it may bottom out
but we're very far from the place where
it bottoms
out if it bottoms out it probably
bottoms out at the plunk length which is
you know 17 orders of magnitude smaller
scale than uh what we're trying to see
at the LHC so we got a long ways to go a
very long ways to go even if it does
bottom out all right those are the basic
facts that I wanted to uh to get out in
front of you they sort of determine
largely how particle physics has
progressed and as I said it has
progressed by going at every stage to
shorter and shorter wavelengths larger
and larger momentum and energy and
smaller and smaller objects
question um would there be any urtic
saying that the wavelength or the size
of the particle you want to look at is
inversely related to the size of the
cyclop draon You're Building you realize
it's a ridiculous ratio but is is that
sort of you need one roughly speaking
roughly speaking yes that's correct
roughly speaking that's right um if you
have a given capacity to accelerate now
what determines the capacity to
accelerate the size of the electric and
the magnetic fields that you can create
so let's suppose you take the largest
fields that you can create in a magnet
made of steel is big and that determines
uh that determines your ability to
acceler accelerate ability to accelerate
means the energy that you can pump into
something per
meter given a meter of accelerator how
much energy can you pump in all right so
to double the amount of energy that
slack produces it would have to be twice
as
long or round or round but uh that
that's right but round gives you another
problem the problem that round gives you
is that when particles move in circular
orbits they radiate and when they
radiate lose energy so let's take the
case of a linear accelerator the longer
the linear accelerator is the higher the
energy that you can pump the particles
to and pretty much linearly linearly
proportional to the size of the
accelerator and it's going to get half
the double the resolution Yeah so
basically resolution times size is the
constant order yeah yeah so if you
wanted to get to this plunk length how
big an accelerator would you have to
have well as I said 17 orders of
magnitude longer than the CERN
accelerator no Universe no I think it's
more like the
Galaxy the ring Engineers yeah I call it
the
gatron
right right
yeah higher I mean the highest cosmic
ray energy are 10 21 electron volts or
something like that uh which is 21 - 9
is
what quick 21 - 9 12 10^ the 12
gev whereas the accelerator in uh well
no it it actually doesn't work the
highest energy cosmic rays are 10^ the
gev um but but the problem is you see
the problem is cosmic rays they may have
this huge energy but they hit stationary
targets whereas in the accelerated CERN
they're going to be colliding
targets and so you get more bang for
your buck from the colliding particles
but still still cosmic rays have much
more energy than U effective energy than
the
accelerators the problem with them is in
order to really do good experiments you
have to have a few a huge flux of
particles you can't do an experiment
with one high energy particle it will
probably miss your target or it probably
won't be a good dead on head-on
collision you don't learn anything from
that you learn very little from that so
what you want is enough flux of
particles so that uh so that you have a
good chance of having a significant
number of head-on collisions that takes
a lot of particles when the targets are
small so I told you how big an
accelerator you would have have to make
now I would tell you how many particles
have to collide in order to see
something
interesting and I once worked out how
much energy it would take to fuel this
accelerator in order that you could do
experiments in a reasonable amount of
time and I think I got something like
100 trillion barrels of oil a
second so uh you need the accelerator as
big as the Galaxy being fueled by
something um I think it was 100 trillion
barrels of oil a second and
uh it's going to be a while till we do
experiments like that yeah yeah right
but these are but these are real
distance scales I mean they really do
come into physics and
um the puzzle and the question is how to
probe them how to get at them without
being able to spend 100 billion barrels
of oil and build a
Galactic size
accelerator so what's the G energy level
hopeful from from the LHC is it hopeful
in what sense in what sense would you
ask is it hopeful compared to this 10 12
G you get from you need it's not
comparable to the 10 the 12 uh GV from
uh
no uh
when you have a particle hitting a
stationary
Target take that 10 12 and take its
square root it's 10 the 6th it's like
having 10 the 6th gev in colliding
particles each one
colliding so if you have two particles
colliding each one with 10 to the 6th
gev it's like having one particle with
10 to the 12th hitting a stationary
particle now 10 the 6 that's a million
gev that's a th000 teev so we're still
very low compared to what uh to what
cosmic rays can
do but if you have a handful of cosmic
rays coming in the chances are that it's
going to do an interesting Collision un
negligible for more please visit us at
stanford.edu